Lois Lenski Collection
Lois Lenski Collection
1927-1967
Lenski, Lois, 1893-1974.
9.75 linear ft.
American author and illustrator of children's books. Collection contains notebooks, manuscripts, book production records, original artwork for her children's books, letters from children, and published material.
149127
Biographical History
Lois Lenski (1893-1974) was an award-winning American author and illustrator of children's books.
Lois Lenski (Mrs. Arthur Covey) was born in Springfield, Ohio, on October 14, 1893. She studied at Ohio State University where she received a B. Sc. degree in education. She also studied at the Westminster School of Art in London where she received an A.S.L. degree.
For over fifty years Lenski pursued her professional career as an illustrator and author of books for children. During that time she illustrated some fifty books for other authors, and wrote and illustrated nearly 100 of her own books. Lenski's writing included picture books and stories for very young children as well as intermediate works for older children and young adults. Although she wrote primarily prose, Lenski also published books of poetry, songs and plays for children. She has received several awards, including the Ohioana Medal (1954), the Newbery Medal (1946), and the Child Study Association Award (1947).
Lenski's work includes Blueberry Corners, The Little Farm, Strawberry Girl, Blue Ridge Billy, Prairie School, Corn-Farm Boy, A Dog Came to School and Little Sioux Girl. [Adapted from www.mlb.ilstu.edu/ressubj/speccol/lenski/History.html]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Lois Lenski Collection is divided into nine series.
Holographic notebooks consists of notes written by Lenski as research for a number of her works, along with two notebooks documenting trips from Georgia to Memphis and from Charleston to Tennessee. Although it appears that originally the notebooks were identified by the title of the book for which the notes were taken, the volumes became disorganized at some point and many of them can no longer be identified as belonging to a particular book.
Holographic and typescript manuscripts consists of original and carbon copy manuscripts and typescripts of books, poems, and songs written by Lenski.
The Miscellaneous subject file contains bibliographies, biographic data, book reviews, illustrations, photostats, printed copies of works, and articles by and about Lenski.
Book dummies includes holographic and page proof galleys and blueprint illustrations, with page layout instructions for several of Lenski's books.
Galley sheets, illustrations, jacket proofs, photographs, and miscellaneous works contains any combination of these items for several of Lenski's books.
Published copies of works include copies of books by Lenski and others, copies of children's magazines featuring pieces by Lenski, and miscellaneous magazines containing articles by or about Lenski.
Artwork contains sets of alphabet blocks and two zinc cuts, all designed by Lenski.
Children's letters contains letters written by children to Lenski over the course of her career. This series is divided into several groups by time period and arranged alphabetically by state or country within each group.
The Subject file contains biographical material, articles about Lenski, a photo album, original art, publishers' brochures, and notes.
Separated Material
The collection originally contained a large number of published copies of Ms. Lenski's works. A few remain in the manuscript collection but the bulk have been transferred to the Rare Books department and cataloged; to locate these please refer to and search for "Lenski, Lois" as author.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Illustrators; Literature -- Children's; Women Authors; Lenski, Lois, 1893-1974.; Children's literature.; Illustrated children's books.; Illustration of books -- United States -- 20th century.; Illustrators -- United States.; Women artists -- United States.; Women authors, American.; Appalachian Region -- Juvenile literature.; Great Plains -- Juvenile literature.; Southern states -- Juvenile literature.; West (U.S.) -- Juvenile literature.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Galley proofs.; Illustrations (layout features); Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Research notes.; Notebooks.; Artists.; Authors.; Illustrators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Lois Lenski, 1967-1968.
Inventory
- Holographic notebooks
  Titles given below are taken from the item, where possible. Where that was not possible, a title has been supplied based on the content; these supplied titles are indicated by square brackets [ ]. Volumes that cannot be identified are filed at the end, listed by first line of the contents.
  - [Original captions] (Box 1)
    These are small slips of paper, each bearing the title of one of Lenski's works. Evidently at some point these were inserted into the volumes to identify them, but they became separated. The works listed, with their geographic settings, are: Blue Ridge Billy [Appalachian Mountains], Boom Town Boy [Oklahoma], Corn Farm Boy [Iowa], Cotton In My Sack [Arkansas], Flood Friday [Connecticut], Houseboat Girl [Mississippi River], Judy's Journey [Alabama], Mama Hattie's Girl [Florida and an unnamed northern city], Prairie School [South Dakota], Strawberry Girl [Florida], We Live by the River [Arkansas], and San Francisco Boy [California].
  - Ark [Arkansas, miscellaneous], 2 folders / 8 volumes (Box 1)
  - Avery (Box 1)
  - Bridgeton N.J. Notes, 2 volumes (Box 1)
  - [Floods and flooding], possibly used for Flood Friday; 4 volumes (Box 1)
  - [Florida], possibly used for Strawberry Girl; 2 folders / 8 volumes (Box 1)
  - Homosassa [Homosassa Springs, Florida], possibly used for Strawberry Girl; 2 notebooks (Box 1)
  - Iowa, possibly used for Corn Farm Boy; 2 volumes (Box 1)
  - Louisiana, 2 volumes (Box 1)
  - [Mama Hattie's Girl?], all three of these items include mention of "Hattie"; 2 volumes (Box 1)
  - Michigan Cherries, one is explicitly titled as such, the other includes notes from numerous towns and cities in Michigan; 2 volumes (Box 1)
  - Miss. River (Box 18)
  - Okla [Oklahoma], 2 folders / 6 volumes (Box 18)
  - S.D. [South Dakota], possibly used for Prairie School; 5 volumes (Box 18)
  - [San Francisco Boy?], one item is titled "S.F." and the other two contain notes about locales in and around San Francisco; 3 volumes (Box 18)
  - Songs [of Mr Small], paper slip reads "Small songs" (Box 18)
  - Texas, possibly used for Texas Tomboy; 8 volumes (Box 18)
  - [Texas] San Angelo, possibly used for Texas Tomboy; 8 volumes (Box 18)
  - Trips: Georgia to Memphis, Charleston to Tennessee, 2 volumes (Box 18)
  - Woodall, possibly more Oklahoma material; 3 volumes (Box 18)
  - Unidentified I, 5 volumes (Box 19)
  - Unidentified II, 4 volumes (Box 19)
- Holographic and typescript manuscripts
  - "All Around Town", Poems/ typescript manuscripts (Box 2)
    "Butcher Shop" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Candy Store" - carbon copy manuscript
    "City Child" - carbon copy manuscript
    "City Street" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Double Decker Bus" - carbon copy manuscript and original typescript manuscript
    "Down In The Subway" - original typescript manuscript
    "I Am The Mailman" - carbon copy manuscript
    "On Main Street" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Our Town" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Penthouse" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Stores In Our Town (The Five and Ten)" - original typescript manuscript
    "Street Cries" - carbon copy manuscript and original typescript manuscript
    "The Park" - carbon copy manuscript
  - "At Our House", original song manuscripts (Box 2)
  - "City Songs", holographs and typescripts (Box 2)
    "City Sidewalk" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Garbage Truck" - original typescript manuscript and 2 carbon copies manuscripts
    "Hot Dog Hot" - carbon copy manuscript
    "In the City" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Newsboy's Song" - holograph and carbon copy manuscripts
    "Songs of the City" - carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "The City Bus" - carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "The Flower Wagon" - carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "Walking on the Sidewalk" - original typescript manuscript with corrections
    "Shoeshine Song" - carbon copy manuscript
    "The Clothes Line" - carbon copy manuscript
    "The Skyscraper" - carbon copy manuscript
  - "Fun And Playtime Songs", typescripts (Box 2)
    "A Hide-out" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Fly-Hop-Skip-Run-Jump" - original typescript manuscript and carbon copy with corrections
    "In the Rain" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Merry-Go-Round" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Riding On My Bike"-
    "Walking On the Sidewalk" - carbon copy manuscript
    "What I like" - carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "I Went For a Walk" - original typescript manuscript
  - "House (Home) Songs", typescripts (Box 2)
    "A Home" - 2 carbon copy manuscripts and original typescript manuscript
    "All Kinds of Homes" - carbon copy manuscript and original typescript manuscript
    "At Our House" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Dinner's Ready" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Hiding" - carbon copy manuscript
    "House By the River" - original typescript manuscript with corrections
    "House or Home" - original typescript manuscript and 2 carbon copies manuscripts
    "I Like To Live In A Trailer" - original typescript manuscript and 2 carbon copies manuscripts
    "My House" - carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "My House Is A Boat" - 2 original typescript manuscripts with corrections and 1 carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "Where People Live" - original typescript manuscript and carbon copy with corrections
  - "Songs of Mr. Small", holographs and typescripts (Box 2)
    "A Customer" - holograph and carbon copy manuscripts
    "Airplane Airplane" - original typescript carbon manuscript
    "Big Mr. Small" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Cactus or Mr. Small's Pony" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Do You Know Big Mr. Small?" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Fireman Brave" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Firetruck" - carbon copy manuscript
    "If I Had A Boat" - carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "If I Had A Tractor" - carbon copy manuscript
    "I like To Live On The Farm" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Just Like A Cowboy" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Little Train" - carbon copy manuscript
    "My Roadside Stand" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Over The Sea" - carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "Ride A red Auto" - carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "The Bird With Silver Wings" - carbon copy manuscript
    "The Gas Station Man" - carbon copy manuscript
    "What Do You Do, Papa Small?" - carbon copy manuscript
  - Original hymn and poem manuscripts, typescripts (Box 2)
    "A Child of God" - carbon copy manuscript
    "A Clean Heart" - carbon copy manuscript
    "A Cry For Help" - carbon copy manuscript
    "A Greater King Than They" - carbon copy manuscript
    "A Safe Answer"
    "Come Unto Me" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Do Unto Others" - original typescript manuscript and carbon copy manuscripts with corrections
    "Early In The Morning" - original typescript and carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "Evening Prayer" - carbon copy manuscript
    "For The Beauty Of The Day" - original typescript manuscript and carbon copy manuscript
    "God's Never Far Off" - carbon copy manuscript
    "In Others' Shoes" - original typescript manuscript and carbon copy manuscript
    "It's All We Have To Give" - carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "I Want To Be Like Jesus" - original typescript and carbon copy manuscript
    "I Was A Stranger" - carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "Kindness" - carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "Long Will We Remember" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Morning Prayer" - original typescript manuscript and carbon copy manuscript
    "My Neighbors" - carbon copy manuscript
    "O Babe In The Manger" - carbon copy manuscript
    "No Room At The Inn" - carbon copy manuscript
    "O Be Joyful" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Our Father Who Art In Heaven" - original typescript manuscript
    "Prayer For Peace" - carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "Shepard, Lonely Shepard" - carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "Song Of Praise" - original typescript manuscript
    "The Angel's Song" - carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "The Door Of My Heart" - carbon copy manuscript
    "The Foxes Have Holes" - carbon copy manuscript
    "The House On The Rock" - carbon copy manuscript
    "The Lord Is My Shepard" - carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "The Lost Sheep" - carbon copy manuscript
    "The Sower" - carbon copy manuscript
    "There's A Song In My Heart" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Treasure In Heaven" - original typescript manuscript and carbon copy manuscript
    "Wake Up Now" - carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "We Are Thy Children" - 2 carbon copies manuscripts
    "We Thank Thee, Lord" - carbon copy manuscript
    "When Jesus Was A Little Boy" - carbon copy manuscript
    "When Others Hate" - original typescript manuscript and carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "When They Come To Thee" - original typescript manuscript and carbon copy manuscript
    "Work Well Done" - original typescript manuscript and carbon copy manuscript
  - "Regional Songs", holographs and typescripts (Box 2)
    "A Big Crop" - original typescript manuscript with corrections
    "Bean-pickers Song" - carbon copy manuscript and original typescript manuscript
    "Big Ole Snapper" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Born Of The Wind" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Children Of America" - 2 carbon copies manuscripts with corrections
    "Cotton In My Sack" - 3 original typescript manuscripts and carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "Down The Cotton Row" - original typescript manuscript and carbon copy manuscripts
    "Git Along There Mule" - holograph and original typescript manuscript and carbon copy manuscript
    "Give Me A Bite" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Go Get Your Hoe" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Island Girl" - holograph and carbon copy manuscripts
    "Jackrabbit" - original typescript manuscript
    "Let's Go Fishing" - original typescript manuscript
    "Lullaby" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Mean Old Wind" - carbon copy manuscript
    "My Daddy Digs Coal" - original typescript manuscript with corrections
    "My Feedsack Dress" - original typescript manuscript and carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "My Uncle Joe" - carbon copy manuscript
    "No Strange Land To Me" - original typescript manuscript with corrections
    "On The Go Again" - original typescript manuscript
    "Out In Texas" - original typescript manuscript
    "Over The Locks" - 2 original typescript manuscript and 2 carbon copies with holograph notations
    "Over The Prairie" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Pancakes" - 2 carbon copies manuscripts
    "Poor Sick Baby" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Strawberry Queen" - original typescript manuscript
    "That Pretty Little Tree" - original typescript manuscript with corrections
    "The Geese Are In The Cotton" - original typescript manuscript and carbon copy manuscript
    "The Gift" - original typescript manuscript
    "(On) The Road" - original typescript manuscript
    "Up And Down The Mountain" - carbon copy manuscript
  - "River Songs", typescripts (Box 2)
    "Down By The River" - original typescript and carbon copy manuscripts
    "The River So Wide" - carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "The Winding River" - carbon copy manuscript with corrections and original typescript manuscript
    "Who'll Take Me Over" - original typescript manuscript and carbon copy manuscript
  - "School Songs", typescripts (Box 2)
    "Lunch At School" - original typescript and carbon copy manuscripts
    "The School Bus" - 3 carbon copies manuscripts with corrections and original typescript manuscript
  - "Very Young Songs", holographs, typescripts, carbon copies (Box 2)
    "A Change Of Heart" - original typescript manuscript
    "A Dog At School" - carbon copy manuscript
    "A Face" - carbon copy manuscript
    "A Letter" - carbon copy manuscript
    "A Man" - carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "A New Dress" - carbon copy manuscript
    "A Tree" - carbon copy manuscript
    "All Around Town" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Animals" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Bedtime" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Champion Pie Baker" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Christmas On The Farm" - original typescript manuscript and carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "Drug Store" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Going For A Ride" - carbon copy manuscript
    "I Can Draw A Horse" - carbon copy manuscript
    "If I Had A Red Dress" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Let's Play House" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Mocking Bird" - original typescript manuscript; carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "My Puppy" - carbon copy manuscript
    "My Shadow" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Neighbors" - carbon copy manuscript
    "On A Summer Day" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Our Dog" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Our House" - carbon copy manuscript
    "People" - original typescript manuscript
    "Our Yard" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Pumpkins" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Rain Song or In The Rain" - original typescript manuscript and carbon copy with corrections
    "Santa's Come" - original typescript manuscript
    "Saturday Night" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Sick" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Sleepin In The Church Yard" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Supermarket" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Ten little Birds" - carbon copy manuscript
    "The Green, Green Grass" - carbon copy manuscript
    "The Red, Red Ribbon" - carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "Traffic Cop" - carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "Turning Around" - carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "Up And Down" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Up And Down The Street" - carbon copy manuscript
    "Where People Live" - carbon copy manuscript with corrections
    "Water" - carbon copy manuscript
  - Miscellaneous poems and songs, holographs; 43 items (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous poems and songs, typescripts; 24 items (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous subject file
  - Bibliographies of Lenski's works, holograph and published pamphlet (2 typescript); 4 items (Box 2)
  - Lois Lenski biographical data-Lois Lenski, Friend of Children (J. B. Lippincott Co.), 1958 (Box 2)
  - Book reviews, 2 items (Box 2)
  - Illustration by Lenski, 6 items (Box 2)
  - Lois Lenski, An Appreciation, 1962; includes published edition (University of North Carolina Press) and original typescripts (Box 2)
  - Music manuscript "Songs For The City", words by Lois Lenski, music by Clyde Robert Bulla; photostat; 29 items (Box 2)
  - Printed copies of work, 14 items (Box 2)
  - Articles by and/or about Lenski, 1947-1958; 6 items (Box 2)
- Book dummies
  - At Our House, first, second, third holographic original dummies (Box 3)
  - Coal Camp Girl, original page dummy of galley proofs and blueprint page dummy with illustrations (Box 3)
  - Flood Friday, page proofs, page dummy with blueprints of illustration (Box 3)
  - Ice Cream Is Good, holographic original dummy hand drawn and painted by Lenski (Box 3)
  - In Our Town (original title) / I Went For A Walk (second title)
    - In Our Town, original holographic dummy (Box 3)
    - I Went For A Walk, second holographic dummy (Box 3)
    - I Went For A Walk, third dummy for blueprints of illustrations (Box 3)
  - Noah's Ark, original holographic dummy with hand drawn and painted illustrations (Box 3)
  - Songs Of Mr. Small, first and second original holographic and typescript dummies with original page layouts and pencil sketches of illustrations (Box 3)
  - We Are Thy Children, original holographic and typescript dummy with original page layout and pencil sketches of illustrations (Box 3)
- Galley sheets, illustrations, jacket proofs, photographs and miscellaneous
  - Coal Camp Girl, illustrations and music page (Box 4)
  - Coal Camp Girl, galley proofs with author's corrections for (Box 4)
  - Coal Camp Girl, galley proofs showing text cut up into pages (Box 4)
  - Coal Camp Girl, original pencil sketches; 2 items (Oversize 1)
  - Flood Friday, original illustrations and music paper; 3 items (Box 4)
  - Indian Captive: The Story of Mary Jemison, illustrations and jacket proofs; 13 items (Box 4)
  - I Went For A Walk At Our House, original illustrations (Box 4)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Noah-Exhibit, illustrations (original and printed), photographs; 13 items (Box 4)
  - Regional books, "Family Life Charts", analysis of Lenski's regional books; 2 items (Box 4)
  - We Are Thy Children, illustrations and acetate overlays; 35 items (Oversize 2)
  - Miscellaneous drawings from Read-To-Me-Storybook, possibly others, 91 items (Oversize 3)
- Published copies of works
  - Out and Away Anthology, 1965 (Box 5)
  - A Guidebook for Teaching Library Skills by M. V. Beck and V. M. Pare, 1965 (Box 5)
  - The Study of Anthropology by P. J. Pelto, 1965 (Box 5)
  - Children's magazines containing articles by Lenski, 1936-1952
    - The How Book, 1946-1952; 3 items (Box 6)
    - Story Parade, 1936-1945; 16 items (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous magazines containing articles by or about Lenski, 1949-1963; 21 items (Box 6)
- Artwork by Lenski
  See also Book dummies, Galley sheets, illustrations, jacket proofs, photographs and miscellaneous, and Subject files.
  - Children's blocks
    - General A B C blocks, 1939; 36 items (Box 7)
    - Story A B C blocks, 1939; 14 items (Box 7)
    - Set of abstract blocks, 18 items (Box 8)
    - General A B C (small set), 1939; 18 items (Box 8)
  - Zinc cuts
    - A-Going To The Westward, 6 items (Box 8)
    - Phebe Fairchild, 4 items (Box 8)
- Children's letters
  - Children's letters, 1927-1950
    - Arkansas (Box 9)
    - California (Box 9)
    - Canada (Box 9)
    - Connecticut (Box 9)
    - Colorado (Box 9)
    - Delaware (Box 9)
    - Florida (Box 9)
    - Georgia (Box 9)
    - Hawaii (Box 9)
    - Illinois (Box 9)
    - Indiana (Box 9)
    - Iowa (Box 9)
    - Kansas (Box 9)
    - Louisiana (Box 9)
    - Maryland (Box 9)
    - Massachusetts (Box 9)
    - Michigan (Box 9)
    - Minnesota (Box 9)
    - Missouri (Box 9)
    - Montana (Box 9)
    - Nebraska (Box 10)
    - New Hampshire (Box 10)
    - New Jersey (Box 10)
    - North Carolina (Box 10)
    - North Dakota (Box 10)
    - New York (Box 10)
    - Ohio (Box 10)
    - Oregon (Box 10)
    - Pennsylvania (Box 10)
    - Rhode Island (Box 10)
    - South Carolina (Box 10)
    - South Dakota (Box 10)
    - Tennessee (Box 10)
    - Texas (Box 10)
    - Utah (Box 10)
    - Virginia (Box 10)
    - Washington (Box 10)
    - Washington D. C. (Box 10)
    - West Virginia (Box 10)
    - Wisconsin (Box 10)
    - Wyoming (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous (no state) (Box 10)
  - Children's letters, April 1951-Oct 1955
    - Alabama (Box 11)
    - Arkansas (Box 11)
    - California (Box 11)
    - Canada (Box 11)
    - Colorado (Box 11)
    - Connecticut (Box 11)
    - Florida (Box 11)
    - Georgia (Box 11)
    - Hawaii (Box 11)
    - Illinois (Box 11)
    - Indiana (Box 11)
    - Iowa (Box 11)
    - Iowa (Box 11)
    - Japan (Box 11)
    - Kansas (Box 11)
    - Kentucky (Box 11)
    - Louisiana (Box 11)
    - Maryland (Box 11)
    - Massachusetts (Box 11)
    - Michigan (Box 11)
    - Minnesota (Box 11)
    - Mississippi (Box 11)
    - Missouri (Box 11)
    - Montana (Box 11)